<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands warning-peece or the history of the gun-powder treason: inlarged with some notable passages not heretofore published. Whereunto is annexed The Act of Parliament for publick thanksgiving upon the fifth day of November yearly. / By T.S.</title>
            <author>Spencer, Thomas, fl. 1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2255_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868966</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868966</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121323</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121323)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 244:E2255[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands warning-peece or the history of the gun-powder treason: inlarged with some notable passages not heretofore published. Whereunto is annexed The Act of Parliament for publick thanksgiving upon the fifth day of November yearly. / By T.S.</title>
                  <author>Spencer, Thomas, fl. 1658.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>80, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for Tho. Pierrepont at the Sun in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659. [i.e. 1658]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.S. = Thomas Spencer.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The historie of the powder treason.</note>
                  <note>Final three leaves = "In the third year of King James. An Act for a publicke thanks-giving to Almighty God, on the fifth day of November every year", with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob:"; the 9 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with an "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121323:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS Warning-Peece: OR The HISTORY of THE Gun-powder Treaſon:</p>
            <p>Inlarged with ſome Notable Paſſages not heretofore Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is Annexed</p>
            <p>The ACT of PARLIAMENT for Publick Thankſgiving upon the Fifth day of <hi>November</hi> yearly.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>They conceive miſcheif, and bring forth vanity,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job 15.35.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Who ſo is wiſe, and will obſerve theſe things: even they ſhall underſtand the loving kindneſs of the Lord,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 107 43.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Pierrepont</hi> at the Sun in <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121323:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121323:2"/>
            <head>TO The Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S time doth weare out the remembrance of actions moſt famous and worthy of marke: ſo Hiſtorie the meſſage of antiquitie doth bring back time with the wonderfull workes thereof, to the knowledge of Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, both for delight and benefit. The memorial of this moſt prodigious Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, which never had any fellow, being almoſt obliterated and forgotten in many places of the land, may be renewed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and preſented to ſucceeding ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, by the uſe of this little Storie. Little Books are fitteſt for little purſes; Such a one as this, whoſe price (I hope) will never give juſt cauſe of repentance to
<pb facs="tcp:121323:3"/>the diſcreet buyer. All that I deſire by it, is, that the great preſerver of man may have everlaſting glory, and our Nation his everlaſting Protection. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend, <hi>Tho. Spencer.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:121323:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Englands Warning-peece,</hi> OR The Hiſtorie of the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Treaſon, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged with ſome notable paſſages, not heretofore publiſhed.</head>
            <p>MAny and ſundry were the Plots and Attempts of Treaſon, againſt our moſt gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous and ever bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed memorie. Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſifth curſed her, and therefore <hi>Parrie</hi> and <hi>Savage</hi> would have ſtabbed her, <hi>Somervil</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne</hi> would have killed her, <hi>Squire</hi> &amp; <hi>Lopez</hi> the Jew would have poyſoned her, but they did all faile of their purpoſes; for God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty bleſſed her, and made her raign long and proſperous; maugre the malice of all her Enemies, both at home and abroad.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121323:4"/>
            <p> When the Pope and his welbeloved Sons (falſely called Catholicks, but truly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) ſaw that no ſorcerie could prevaile againſt her, they did then caſt about how they might ſerve their own turne, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their own cauſe by her Majeſties im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Succeſſor. To this end Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the eight (a little before her death) ſent two Bulls or Letters into <hi>England,</hi> one after another, wherein he did forbid any man to claim the Crown, and take upon him the Rule and Government of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Nation, that would not conforme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> acknowledge the Supremacie of her head the Pope, and ſtoop to his lure; yea death was to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured by his beloved Sons, rather then ſuch a one ſhould be admitted, that would tolerate any of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>And to debarr the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> of his right of ſucceſſion, he did liberally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon him the diſgraceful names of a Heretick, a Schiſmatick, an Apoſtate, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Julian. Such were the terrible words of his thunder. Much about this time <hi>Robert Parſons</hi> the Jeſuit wrote a Book of honorable deſcents, and put it forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Dolmax,</hi> wherein he did intitle the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as being deſcended from <hi>Katha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:121323:4"/>the Daughter of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Caunt</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> the fourth Son of our King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, who was married to <hi>Henry</hi> the third King of <hi>Castile</hi> and <hi>Leon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in another book he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>His</hi> Philopater. Sect. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>That it is the opinion both of Divines &amp; Lawyers, That if any Chriſtian Prince ſhal fall from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, and ſeek to draw others from the ſame, he doth preſently fall from all princely power and dignity.</q>
               <note place="margin">Viſib. Monar. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4,</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Sanders</hi> another bird of the ſame wing, ſaith, <q>That the King that wil not ſubmit himſelf to the authority of the Pope, ought not to be tolerated, but his Subjects ought to chuſe another in his place, aſſoon as may be.</q> Theſe diplomati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Jeſuitical writings, gave life and beginning to the greateſt, the rareſt, the vileſt Treaſon, that ever was invented, plotted, attempted, againſt Prince and People, famous throughout the world for the horrible infamy thereof (the eternal ſhame of Poperie) as ſhal be ſhewed in the courſe of our Hiſtorie.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſoure and twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One Thouſand ſix hundred and two, Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> (a Princeſs full of happy daies, but fuller of immortal Trophees of honor)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121323:5"/>did change her corruptible Crown in this World, for an incorruptible in Heaven, and within four hours after her deceaſe, by the grave and wiſe Councel that ſhe left behind her, <hi>James</hi> the ſixt of <hi>Scotland</hi> was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> at the Court-gate at <hi>Richmond,</hi> which did much rejoyce the hearts of the godly people in <hi>England</hi> when they heard of it. And in the ſweet and pleaſant moneth of <hi>May,</hi> his Majeſty made a ſafe arrival at <hi>London,</hi> where he was received with great joy and acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> did ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed and wondred, when they heard that his Majeſty had gotten the poſſeſſion of two Kingdoms without the ſhedding of a drop of blood. Many of them ſent their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, and the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> (who was brother to his Wife the Queen) came in his own perſon, to congratulate the greatneſs of his fortunes. It was now a rare ſight in <hi>London</hi> to ſee two Kings walke peaceably together in the ſtreets.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty for ſome reaſons did deferr his Coronation, untill the twenty fifth of <hi>July,</hi> In the meane while ſome turbulent and diſcontented ſpirits plotted a conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and purpoſed to ſurpriſe the King and Prince <hi>Henry</hi> his eldeſt Son, being inſtigated and perſwaded thereunto, by <hi>Watſon</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121323:5"/>
               <hi>Clarke</hi> two Popiſh Prieſts, who told them that the Act was lawfull, for that the King was no King before he was Crowned. The other perſons of note involved in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, were, <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Wilton, Henry Brooke,</hi> Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> Sir <hi>Griffin Markham,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Parham, George Bro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke</hi> Brother to the Lord <hi>Cobham, Bartholomew Brookesly,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Copley;</hi> All which were indited; Sir <hi>Edward Parham</hi> was acquitted by the Jury, the reſt were found guilty and condemned. <hi>George Brooke,</hi> and <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clarke</hi> the two Prieſts were executed. All the reſt were graciouſly pardoned by his Majeſty; at which example of mercy, the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wiſhed, that they might ſacrifice their lives, to gain the love and favor of ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful a Prince. But clemency to offenders makes men bold to offend. One Treaſon is paſt, and a greater follows at the heeles thereof. For in the ſame yeer the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent the Devil doth put it into the heart of <hi>Robert Catesby</hi> of <hi>Aſhby</hi> in the County of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> Eſquire, to deſtroy the King with Gunpowder, by blowing up the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe, when his Majeſty, the Queen, the Prince, the Duke, the choyceſt of the Nobility and Gentry, were there aſſembled, for doing the turne; moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121323:6"/>to their places and degrees. And this damnable device, he did maintain to be holy and lawful, upon this ground of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; That if by the two Bulls or Letters of Pope Clement the eight,<note place="margin">See the Hiſt. of <hi>France,</hi> P. 1196.</note> they ought not to have received the King into the Kingdome; then by a greater reaſon, being received, the Pope would have him made away; as if Kings, Free Princes, and States were to live but at the pleaſure of the Pope. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorious doctrine of the Joſuits, did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe add much fuel to this fiery enterprize, which was firſt made known and revealed by <hi>Cateshy</hi> to <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> of <hi>Huddington</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> when they met together at <hi>London,</hi> who gave his conſent and approbation thereunto, And ſhortly after went into <hi>Flanders</hi> to negotiate with <hi>Baldwine</hi> the Jeſuite, with the Conſtable, with <hi>Owen,</hi> with <hi>Faewkes,</hi> and alſo with Sir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> who for many yeers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did lurk in thoſe parts of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> that were under the obedience of <hi>Albertus</hi> Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and <hi>Clara Iſabella</hi> his Wife, the Daughter of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and durſt not come into <hi>England.</hi> For this was that Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> who (contrary to his Oath) did treacherouſly deliver up <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>venter</hi> a rich Town in <hi>Oven
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121323:6"/>Yſſell,</hi> to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which had bin gotten a little before by <hi>Robert Dudley</hi> Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> ſent into the low Countries with ſome conſiderable Forces by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to aid the <hi>Dutch</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> but the Town was regained ſhortly after by the States of <hi>Holland.</hi> He that is falſe to God will be falſe to Man, and when opportunity ſerves, will keep no faith with them that are no better then Heretikes in his account.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Winter</hi> had conferred with the parties aforeſaid, and had imparted to them ſo much of his minde, as he thought convenient at this time, he returned back into <hi>England,</hi> and brought with him <hi>Guide Fawks,</hi> a very deſperate Souldier, and a monſtrous inſtrument of mercileſe cruelty. And when they came to <hi>London,</hi> they met with <hi>Robert Catesby, Thomas Percy,</hi> and <hi>John Wright,</hi> at a houſe behinde St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Church without <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> where they ſpake of doing ſome thing, but firſt they thought it fit, to take an Cath of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie, which they gave to each other up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Primer, the contents whereof here followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YOu ſhall swear by the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and by the Sacrament you now purpoſe to receive, never to diſcloſe, directly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121323:7"/>nor indirectly, by word or circumſtance, the matter that ſhall be propoſed to you to keep ſecret, nor deſiſt from the Execution thereof, untill the reſt ſhall give you leave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for their further confirmation, they went into a more private chamber, and there heard Maſs, and received the bleſſed Sacrament, at the hands of <hi>William Gerrard</hi> a Prieſt, who told them that it was better that ſome Innocents did periſh with the nocent, for the advantage of the Catholicks, rather then the ſervice ſhould quaile, the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of time and occaſion ſo requiring it. And now did <hi>Catesby</hi> and <hi>Winter</hi> diſcloſe the buſineſs to the reſt; wherefore they took the Oath, which they all approved. And <hi>Percy</hi> by the Authority of the reſt was ſent to take ſome houſe or lower roome either under or near the Parliament houſe, to lay in the Powder which was to be bought by <hi>Winter</hi> and <hi>Fawkes.</hi> Now while this Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrices Egge (horrible Treaſon) was hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to the end that it might ſucceed well, and breake forth into a Baſiliske a flying and fire-breathing Serpent, whoſe deadly eye might deſtroy both Prince and People in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, the Papiſts gave themſelves to their devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Prayers both at home and abroad. For although the vulgar ſort knew not of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121323:7"/>the particulars of the damnable deſign, yet they had a general notion, and confuſed knowledge of ſome thing to be done in the Parliament, for the good of their Church.</p>
            <p>And the Prieſts and Jeſuits themſelves, did uſually conclude their Maſſes, and obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifices with theſe verſes made by <hi>Henry Garnet</hi> Provincial over the Jeſuits here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Gentem auferte perfidam credentium de finibus,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Chriſto laudes debitas perſolvamus alacriter.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I Engliſh thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Even from the Coaſts of faithfull men A faithleſs Nation take,</l>
               <l>That chearfully to Chriſt our Lord We may due praiſes make.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And others prayed,<note place="margin">See <hi>Speed</hi> his Chron.</note> (as they were taught thus;</p>
            <p>Proſper Lord their paines, that labour in thy cauſe day and night, let Hereſie va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away like ſmoake, let the memory of it periſh with a crack, like the ruine and fall of a broken houſe:</p>
            <p>Hereby alluding to their working in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121323:8"/>Myne, the mounting ſmoak of the Powder, and the violent fall of the Parliament houſe.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Flanders Baldwine</hi> was not ſlack, to improve his Intereſt in Heaven, for the ſpeeding of their great errand.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Rome Parſons</hi> the Jeſuite, being Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of that Colledge which was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the thirteenth, for Engliſh Fugitives and diſcontented malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, did give order to the Students of the houſe, after their ordinary devotions were ended, to pray for ſome extraordinary thing.<note place="margin">— Orate procon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſione Turcae.</note> One while they muſt pray for the converſion of the <hi>Turke,</hi> ſome two or three daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Another while they muſt pray as long for the Captives in <hi>England,</hi> meaning the Papiſts that were in Priſon. But for two moneths together before the day appointed for the execution of their bloodie deſign,<note place="margin">Orate pro Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis in Anglia.</note> 
               <hi>Parſons</hi> commanded them to pray, for the intention of their Father Rector; which made the Students of the houſe wonder what their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rectors intention ſhould be.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orate pro intentione Patris Rectoris.</hi> They had ſet formes of Prayer for theſe things made by <hi>Parſons.</hi>
               </note> But when they heard of a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Treaſon diſcovered in <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:121323:8"/>ſixteen of them forſook the Colledge, and came over the <hi>Alpes down</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> waiting for a better ſeaſon to return home; with ſome of which who forſook the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and embraced the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, I had ſome conference. The King began his Raign (as we have ſhewed) upon the foure and twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> the laſt day of the year, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the date of the Lawyers, in the yeer of our Lord God, one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and two. And in the Summer Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following, and in part of the Autumnal, the Plague in <hi>London</hi> made a lamentable ravage upon mankind; the weekly Bills of mortalitie (I very well remember) were exceeding great. But when it pleaſed God to lighten his hand, and relent the violence of his devouring Angel againſt the people of that City, giving good hope that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection was come to a period, then did his Majeſty call his Parliament upon the nineteenth day of the next <hi>March,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſeventh of <hi>Iuly,</hi> concluded the firſt Seſſions thereof, and adjourned it to the ſeventh of <hi>February</hi> in the ſecond yeer of his raign And before that time came, he did adjourne it again to the ſift of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the third yeer of his raign, and in the yeer of our Lord one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121323:9"/>and five, which proves a moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able date by reaſon of this monſtrous and never enough abhorred Treaſon. This long time between the firſt and the ſecond Seſſion of the Parliament, gave good leiſure and liberty to thoſe of the Conſpiracy, not only to make a large proviſion of Powder, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots, Billets, Barres, and whatſoever elſe they thought neceſſarie for the execution of their deviliſh device; but alſo to travell into forraine Countries, to viſit their Friends and welwiſhers, and to ſollicite them for their aid and beſt aſſiſtance when need ſhould require it. <hi>Winter</hi> makes a journey to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alladolit</hi> in <hi>Castile,</hi> and <hi>Fawkes</hi> returnes into <hi>Flanders</hi> to conſult with Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> and the reſt, and then goes over the <hi>Alpes</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the bleſſing of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the ſift, and to take the Counſel of Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> a bitter enemy to his own Country. In the latter end of the Summer preceding their intended fatal ſift of <hi>November,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne back into <hi>England,</hi> and doe finde their Diabolical machination in a ſafe and ſecure condition. The time for the ſitting of the Parliament doth now begin to draw nigh, and the Nobility and Gentry that had places in that high Court, did make preparation to come up to <hi>London.</hi> The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121323:9"/>conſpirators likewiſe did make all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration they could to give them the blow, even that blow that ſhould have been the common ruine of us all. Curſed may it be called or bleſſed; or both? curſed in reſpect of the intent, but bleſſed for ever in reſpect of the event. For when we were white for their harveſt, and ready to be cut down by them, then, even then did the Almighty, by his gracious Providence, bring to light and diſcoverie, this infernal and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Plot, as ſhall be ſhewed in the next part of the Hiſtory wherein I will follow the Original,<note place="margin">Carleton <hi>and</hi> Speed.</note> as others have done before me</p>
            <p>The Saturday of the week, immediatly preceding the Kings return from his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting exerciſe at <hi>Royſton,</hi> (which was upon a Thurſday ten daies before the Parliament) the Lord <hi>Montegle,</hi> Son and Heire to the Lord <hi>Morley,</hi> being in his own lodging ready to goe to ſupper, at ſeaven of the Clock at night, one of his footmen (whom he had ſent of an errand over the ſtreet) was met by an unknown Man of a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tall perſonage, who delivered him a Letter, charging him to put it in my Lord his Maſters hands; which my Lord no ſooner received but having broken it up, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the ſame to be of an unknown and ſomewhat unlegible hand, and without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121323:10"/>either date or ſubſcription; did call one of his men unto him, for helping him to read it. But no ſooner did he conceive the ſtrange contents thereof, although he was ſomewhat perplexed what conſtruction to make of it (as whether of a matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as indeed it was, or whether ſome fooliſh deviſed paſquil, by ſome of his Enemies, to ſcare him from his attendance at the Parliament) yet did he as a moſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and loyal Subject, conclude not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale it, what ever might come of it. Whereupon, notwithſtanding the lateneſs and darkeneſs of the night in that ſeaſon of the yeare, he preſently repaired to his Majeſties Palace at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the ſame to the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> his Majeſties principal Secretary. Whereupon the ſaid Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> having read the Letter and heard the manner of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it to his hands, did greatly encourage and commend my Lord for his diſcretion, telling him plainly that whatſoever the purpoſe of the Letter might prove here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, yet did this accident put him in minde of diverſe advertiſements he had received from beyond the Seas, wherewith he had acquainted aſwell the King himſelf, as divers of his Privy Counſellors, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome buſineſs the Papiſts were in, both
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121323:10"/>at home and abroad, making preparations for ſome combination amongſt them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Parliament time. for enabling them to deliver to the King ſome Petition for toleration of Religion, which ſhould be delivered in ſome ſuch order, and ſo well backed, as the King ſhould be loth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their requeſts, like the ſturdy Beggars, craving almes with one open hand, but carrying a ſtone in the other in caſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal. And therefore did the Earle of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> conclude with the Lord <hi>Montegle</hi> that he would in regard of the Kings abſence, impart the ſame Letter to ſome more of his Majeſties Councell; whereof my Lord <hi>Mountegle</hi> liked well: only added this by way of proteſtation, that whatſoever the event hereof might prove, it ſhould not be imputed to him, as proceeding from too light and too ſuddain an apprehenſion, that he delivered this Letter, being only moved thereunto for demonſtration of his ready devotion, and care for preſervation of his Majeſty and the State. And thus did the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> preſently acquaint the Lord <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> with the ſaid Letter. Whereupon they two in the preſence of the Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi> calling to minde the former intelligence already mentioned, which ſeemed to have ſome relation with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121323:11"/>this Letter; The tender care which they ever carried to the preſervation of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties perſon made them apprehend, that ſome perillous attempt, did thereby appear to be intended againſt the ſame, which did the more neerly concern, the ſaid Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> to have a care of, in regard that it doth belong to the charge of his Office, to overſee aſwell all places of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie where his Majeſty is to repair, as his Highneſs own private houſes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did the ſaid two Counſellors conclude, that they ſhould joyn unto themſelves three more of the Council, to wit, the Lord Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, the Earles of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,,</hi> to be alſo particularly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with this accident, who having all of them concurred together, to the reexamina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the contents of the ſaid Letter, they did cenclude, that how ſlight a matter it might at the firſt appear to be, yet was it not abſolutely to be contemned, in reſpect of the care which it behooved them to have of the preſervation of his Majeſties perſon. But yet reſolved, for two reaſons, firſt to acquaint the King himſelf with the ſame, before they proceeded to any further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition in the matter, aſwell for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation and experience they had of his Majeſties fortunate Judgment, in cleering
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121323:11"/>and ſolving of obſcure riddles and doubtful myſteries; as alſo becauſe the more time would in the mean while be given for the practice to ripen, if any was, whereby the diſcovery might be the more cleer and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and the ground of proceeding there upon, more ſafe, juſt, and eaſie. And ſo according to their determination,<note place="margin">The Letter ſhewed to the King.</note> did the ſaid Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> repair to the King in his Gallery upon Friday, being <hi>Alhollow</hi> day in the afternoon, which was the day after his Majeſties arrival, and none but himſelf being preſent with his Highneſs at that time, where, without any other ſpeech or judgement given of the Letter, but only relating ſimplie the forme of the delivery thereof, he preſented it to his Majeſty. The contents whereof follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MY Lord, out of theleve I beare to ſome of your friends. I have a care of your preſervation. Thereſore I would adviſe you, as you fender your life, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe ſo me excuſe to ſhift off your affen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at this Parliament. For God and Man have toncurred to puniſh the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of this time. And thinke not nightly of this Aovertiſement, but retire your ſelf into your Country, where you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121323:12"/>may expect the event in ſafety. For though there be no appeatance of any ſtir, yet I ſay, they ſhall receive a terrible blow this Parliament, and yet they ſhall net ſee who burts them. This Counſell is not to be contemned, becauſe it may doe you good, and can doe you no barme; for the danger is paſt ſo ſoon as you have burnt the Letter. And I hope God will give you the grace, to make good vſe of it. To whoſe holy profection I commend you</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King no ſooner read the Letter, but after a little pauſe, and then reading it over againe, he delivered his judgement of it in ſuch ſort, as he thought it was not to be contemned, for that the ſtyle of it ſeemed to be more quick and pithie, then is uſual to be in any Paſquil or Libel (the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities of idle brains:) But the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> perceiving the King to apprehend it deeplier then he looked for, knowing his nature, told him that he thought by one ſentence in it that it was like to be written by ſome Foole or Madman, reading to him this ſentence in it, <hi>For the danger is paſt as ſoon as you have burnt the Letter,</hi> which he ſaid was likely to be the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a Foole: if the danger was paſt o ſoon as the Letter was burnt, the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121323:12"/>behoved to be of little availe, when the burning might make the danger to be eſchewed. But the King by the contrary conſidering the former ſentence in the Letter, <hi>That they ſhould receive a terrible blow at this Parliament, and yet ſhould not ſee who hurt them,</hi> joyning it to the ſentence immediately following, already alleadged, did thereupon conjecture, That the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger mentioned, ſhould be ſome ſuddain danger, by blowing up of Powder. For no other Inſurrection, Rebellion, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other private and deſperate Attempt could be committed or attemoted, in time of Parliament, and the Authors thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, except it were only by a blowing up of Powder, which might he performed by one baſe knave in a dark corner; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he was move to interpret and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue the latter ſentence in the Letter (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) againſt all ordinary ſenſe and conſtruction in Grammar, as if by theſe words, <hi>For the danger is paſt as ſoon as you have burned the Letter,</hi> ſhould be cloſely underſtood the ſuddainty and quickneſs of the danger, which ſhould be as quickly performed and at an end, as that paper ſhould be of bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing up in the fire; tnrning that word of <hi>as ſoon</hi> to the ſenſe of <hi>as quickly;</hi> And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121323:13"/>therefore wiſhed that before his going to the Parliament, the under rooms of the Parliament houſe might be well and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ſearched. But the Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> wondring at his Majeſties Commentary, which he knew to be ſo farre contrary to his ordinary and naturall diſpoſition, who did ever ſin upon the other ſide, in not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending nor truſting due Advertiſements of practiſes and perils, when he was truly informed of them; whereby he had many times drawn himſelf into many deſperate dangers; and interpreting rightly this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary caution at this time to proceed from the vigilant care he had of the whole State, more then of his own perſon, which could not but have all periſhed together, if this deſignement had ſucceeded; He thought good to diſſemble ſtill unto the King, that there had been any juſt cauſe of ſuch apprehenſion. And ending the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe with ſome merry jeſt upon this Subject, as his cuſtome is, took his leave for that time. But though he ſeemed ſo to neglect it to his Majeſty; yet his cuſtomable and watchfull care of the King and the State ſtill boyling within him; And having with the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> laid up in his heart the Kings ſo ſtrange judgement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it; He could not be at reſt, till
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121323:13"/>he had acquainted the foreſaid Lords, what had paſſed between the King and him in private; Whereupon they were all ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to renew again, the memorie of the ſame purpoſe to his Majeſty, as it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed that he ſhould the next day, being Saturday, repair to his Highneſs; which he did in the ſame privy Gallery, and renewed the memory thereof, the Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> then being preſent with the King. At what time it was determined, that the ſaid Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> ſhould according to his Cuſtome and Office, view all the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment houſes; both above and below, and conſider what likelihood or appearance of any ſuch danger might poſſibly be gathered by the ſight of them. But yet aſwell for ſtaying of idle rumors, as for being the more able to diſcerne any myſtery, the nearer that things were in readineſs, his journey thither was ordained to be deferred till the afternoon before the ſitting down of the Parliament, which was upon the Monday following. At what time he (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this concluſion) went to the Parliament houſe accompanied with my Lord <hi>Mountegle,</hi> being in reale to the Kings ſervice earneſt and curious, to ſee the event of that accident, whereof he had the fortune to be the firſt diſcovered: Where,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121323:14"/>having viewed all the lower rooms, he found in the vault under the upper houſe, great ſtore and proviſion of Billets, Fagots, and Coales. And enquiring of <hi>Whyneard</hi> keeper of the Wardrobe. to what uſe he had put thoſe lower rooms and cellars; he told him, that <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> had hired both the houſe and part of the Cellar or vault under the ſame, and that the Wood and Coale therein was the ſaid Gentlemans own proviſion. Whereupon the Lord <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> caſting his eye aſide, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a fellow ſtanding in a corner there, calling himſelf the ſaid <hi>Percies</hi> man &amp; keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of that houſe for him, but was indeed <hi>Cuido Fawkes</hi> the owner of that hand which ſhould have acted that monſtrous Tragedy.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> looking upon all things with a heedfull indeed, yet in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, but with a careleſs and rackleſs eye (as became ſo wiſe and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent a Miniſter) he preſently addreſſed himſelf to the King, in the ſaid Privy Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, where in the preſence of the Lord <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> the Lord <hi>Admiral,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Worceſter, Northampton,</hi> and <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> he made his report what he had ſeen and obſerved there, noting that <hi>Mountegle</hi> had told him, That he no ſooner heard <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> named to be the poſſeſſor of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121323:14"/>that houſe, but conſidering both his back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs in Religion, and the old dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in friendſhip between himſelf and the ſaid <hi>Percy,</hi> he did greatly ſuſpect the matter, and that the Letter ſhould come from him. The ſaid Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> alſo told, That he did not wonder a little at the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary great proviſion of Wood and Coale in that houſe, where <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> had ſo ſeldome occaſion to remain. As likewiſe it gave him in his minde that his man looked like a very tall and deſperate fellow.</p>
            <p>This could not but encreaſe the Kings former apprehenſion and jealouſie: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he inſiſted (as before) that the Houſe was narrowly to be ſearched and that thoſe Billets and Coales would be ſearched to the bottom, it being moſt ſuſpitious, that they were laid there, only for covering of the powder. Of this ſame mind alſo were all the Counſellors then preſent. But upon the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of making the ſearch was it long debated. For upon the one ſide they were all ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Kings ſafety, that they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, that there could not be too much caution uſed for preventing his danger. And yet upon the other part, they were all extreame loth and dainty, that in caſe this Letter ſhould prove to be nothing but the evaporation of an idle brain, then a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121323:15"/>ſearch being made, and nothing found, ſhould not only turn to the general ſcandal of the King and the State as being ſo ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious of every light and frivolous toy, but likewiſe lay an illfavored imputation upon the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> one of his Majeſties greateſt Subjects and Counfellors, this <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> being his kinſman and moſt confident familiar: And the rather were they curious in this point, knowing how far the King deteſted, to be thought ſuſpitious or jealous, of any of his good Subjects, though of the meaneſt degree. And therefore though they all agreed upon the maine ground, which was to provide for the ſecurity of the Kings perſon, yet did they much differ in the circumſtances, by which this action might be beſt carried with leaſt din and occaſion of ſlander. But the King himſelf ſtill perſiſting that there were divers ſhrewd appearances, and that a narrow ſearch of thoſe places could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice no man that was innocent, he at laſt plainly reſolved them, That either muſt all the parts of thoſe roomes be narrowly ſearched, and no poſſibility of danger left unexamined, or elſe he and they all muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve not to meddle in it at all, but plainly to goe the next day to the Parliament, and leave the ſucceſs to fortune, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121323:15"/>they would be loth to take upon their conſciences; for in ſuch a caſe as this, an halfe doing was worſe then no doing at all. Wherefore it was at laſt concluded. That nothing ſhould be left unſearched in thoſe houſes, And yet for the better colour and ſtay of rumour, in caſe nothing were found, it was thought meet that upon a pretence of <hi>Whyneards</hi> miſſing ſome of the Kings ſtuff or Hangings, which he had in keeping, all thoſe roomes ſhould be nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ripped for them. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was Sir <hi>Thomas Knever</hi> (a Gentleman of his Majeſties privie Chamber) employed, being a Juſtice of Peace in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and one of whoſe ancient fidelity both the late Queen and our now Soveraign hath had large proof: who according to the truſt committed unto him, went about the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night next after, to the Parliament houſe, accompanied with ſuch a ſmall number as was fit for that errand. But before his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into the houſe, finding <hi>Thomas Percies</hi> alledged man ſtanding without the dores his clothes and boots on at ſo dead a time of the night he reſolved to apprehend him, as he did, and thereafter went forward to the ſearching of the houſe, whereafter he had cauſed to be overturned ſome of the Billets and Coales, he firſt found one of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121323:16"/>ſmall Barrels of Powder, and after all the reſt, to the number of thirty ſix Barrels great and ſmall. And there after fearching the fellow, whom he had taken, found three matches, and all other inſtruments fit for blowing up the powder, ready upon him, which made him inſtantly confeſs his own guiltineſs, declaring alſo unto him, That if he had hapned to be within the houſe when he tookhim, as he was immediatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (at the ending of his work) he would not have failed to have blown him up houſe and all.</p>
            <p>Thus after Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> had cauſed the wretch to be ſurely bound, and well guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the company he had brought with him, he himſelf returned back to the Kings Palace, and gave warning of his ſucceſs to the Lord <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> who immed atly warning all the reſt of the Counſell that lay in the houſe, as ſoon as they could get themſelves ready, came with their fellow Counfellers to the Kings Bed-Chamber, being at that time near four of the Clock in the morning. And at the firſt entry of the Kings Chamber door the Lord <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> being not any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to conceale his joy for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſo great a danger, told the King in a confuſed haſte, that all was found and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121323:16"/>and the Traytor in hands, and faſt bound.</p>
            <p>Then order being firſt taken for ſending for the reſt of the Council that lay in the Towne, The Priſoner himſelf was brought into the houſe, where in reſpect of the ſtrangeneſs of the accident, no man was ſtaid from the ſight or ſpeaking with him. And within a while after, the Council did examine him, who ſeemed to put on a Roman reſolution; did both to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and to every other perſon that ſpake with him that day, appeare ſo conſtant and ſetled upon his grounds, as we all thought we had found ſome new <hi>Mutius Scaevola</hi> borne in <hi>England.</hi> For notwithſtanding the horror of the Fact, the guilt of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, his ſuddain ſurpriſing, the terror which ſhould have been ſtrucken in him, by coming into the preſence of ſo grave a Council, and the reſtleſs and conſuſed queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that every man all that day did vex him with; yet was his countenance ſo far from being dejected, as he often ſmiled in ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner, not only avowing the Fact, but repenting only with the ſaid <hi>Scaevola,</hi> his fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling in the execution thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (he ſaid) the Devil and not God was the diſcoverer; anſwering quickly to every mans objection, ſcoſſing at any idle queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121323:17"/>which were propounded unto him, and jeſting with ſuch as he thought had no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to examine him. All that day could the Council get nothing out of him touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his complices, refuſing to anſwer to any ſuch queſtions which he thought might diſcover the plot, and laying all the blame upon himſelf; whereupon he ſaid he was moved only for Religion and conſcience ſake denying the King to be his lawfull So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, or the anoynted of God in reſpect he was an Heretick, and giving himſelf no other name then <hi>John Johnſon,</hi> ſervant to <hi>Thomas Percy.</hi> But the next morning being carried to the <hi>Tower,</hi> he did not there remaine above two or three daies, being twice or thrice in that ſpace re-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, and, and the rack only offered and ſhewed unto him, when the mask of his Roman fortitude did viſibly begin to wear and ſlide of his face; And then did he begin to confeſs part of the truth, and thereafter to open the whole matter, as doth appear by his depoſitions immediatly following.</p>
            <div type="deposition">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:121323:17"/>
               <head>The true Copy of the Depoſitions of <hi>Guido Fawkes,</hi> taken in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Counſellors, whoſe names are under written.</head>
               <p>I confeſs that a practice in general was firſt broken unto me, againſt his Majeſty for releif of the Catholick canſe, and not invented or propounded by my ſelf. And this was firſt propounded unto me about <hi>Eaſter</hi> laſt was twelve moneth beyond the Seas, in the Low Countries of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dukes obeiſance, by <hi>Thomas Winter,</hi> who came thereupon with me into <hi>England,</hi> and there we imparted our purpoſe to three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen more, namely <hi>Robert Catesby, Thomas Peter,</hi> and <hi>John Wright;</hi> who all five conſulting together of the means how to excute the ſame, and taking a vow among our ſelves for ſecre<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>Cateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> pro pounded to have it performed by Gunpowder, and by making a Myne under the upper-houſe of Parliament; which place we made choice of the rather, becauſe Religion having been unjuſtly ſuppreſſed there, it was fitteſt that Juſtioce and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be executed there.</p>
               <p>This being reſolved amongſt us, <hi>Thomas
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121323:18"/>Percy</hi> hired and houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for that purpoſe, near adjoyning to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe, and there we begun to make our Myne about the eleventh of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1604.</p>
               <p>The five that firſt entred into the work, were, <hi>Thomas Percy, Robert Catesby, Thomas Winter, John Wright,</hi> and my ſelf; and ſoon after me took another unto us, <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Wright,</hi> having ſworn him alſo, and taken the Sacrament for ſecreſie. When we came to the every foundation of the wall of the houſe, which was about three yards thick, and found it a matter of great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, we took unto us another Gentleman, <hi>Robert Winter,</hi> in like manner with Oath and Sacrament as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>It was about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> when we brought our Myne unto the Wall, and about <hi>Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> we had wrought the Wall half through. And whilſt they were in working, I ſtood as Sentinell to diſcry any man that came neer, whereof I gave them warning, and ſo they ceaſed untill I gave notice again to proceed.</p>
               <p>All we ſeven lay in the houſe, and had ſhot and Powder, being reſolved to die in that place before we ſhould yeeld or be taken.</p>
               <p>As they were working upon the Wall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121323:18"/>they heard a ruſhing in a Cellar of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of Coales, whereupon we feared we had been diſcovered; and they ſent to go to the Cellar, who finding that the Coales were a ſelling, and that the Cellar was to be let, viewing the commodity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for our purpoſe, <hi>Percy</hi> went and hired the ſame for yeerly rent.</p>
               <p>We had before this provided and brought into the houſe twenty Barrels of Powder, which we removed into the Cellar, and covered the ſame with Billet: and Fagots, which were provided for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>About <hi>Eaſter</hi> the Parliament being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued till <hi>October</hi> next, we diſperſed our ſelves, and I returned into the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries by advice and direction of the reſt, aſwell to acquaint <hi>Owen</hi> with the Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the plot, as alſo leaſt by my longer ſtay, I might have grown ſuſpitious, and ſo have come in queſtion.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Percy</hi> having the Key of the Cellar, laid in more Powder and Wood into it. I returned about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>September</hi> next, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Key again of <hi>Percy</hi> we brought in more Powder and Billers <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cover the ſame again, and ſo I went fer a time into the Country till the 30 of <hi>October.</hi> It was further reſolved amongſt us, that the fame
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121323:19"/>day that this Act ſhould have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, ſome other of our confederates ſhould have ſurpriſed the perſon of the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Kings eldeſt Daughter, who was kept in <hi>Warwickſhire</hi> at the Lord <hi>Haringtons</hi> houſe, and preſently have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed her Queen, having a project of a Proclamation ready for that purpoſe; wherein we made no mention of alteration of Religion, nor would have we avowed the deed to beours, untill we ſhould have had power enough to make our party good, and then we would have avowed both. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Duke <hi>Charles</hi> the Kings ſecond Son, we had ſundry conſultations how to ſeiſe on his perſon. But becauſe we found no means how to compaſs it (the Duke being kept neer <hi>London,</hi> where we had not forces enough) we reſolved to ſerve our turne with the Lady <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Commiſſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward Somer ſet</hi> Earle of <hi>Worceſter, Charles Howard</hi> Earle of <hi>Notingham, Thomas Howard</hi> Earle of <hi>Suffolke, Charles Blont</hi> Earle of <hi>Devonſhire, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Howard</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton, Robert Cicil</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisbury</hi> Lord Treaſurer, <hi>John Erſkeine</hi> Earle of <hi>Marre, William
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121323:19"/>Conſtable</hi> Viſcount <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Sir <hi>Fohn Popham,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> Sir <hi>William Waad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here let us leave <hi>Fawkes</hi> in a lodging fit for ſuch a gueſt, and taking time to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe upon his conſcience; and turne our ſelves to that part of the Hiſtory, which concernes the fortune of the reſt of his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers in this abominable Treaſon. The news was no ſoouer ſpread abroad that morning, which was upon a Tueſday the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> and the firſt day deſigned for that Seſſion of Parliament but ſome of thoſe conſpirators, namely <hi>Winter,</hi> and the two <hi>Wrights</hi> brothers, thought it high time to haſten out of the Town (for <hi>Catesby</hi> was gone the night before, and <hi>Percy</hi> at foure of the Clock in the morning, the ſame day of the diſcovery) and all of them held their courſe, with more haſte then good ſpeed, to <hi>Dunchurch</hi> upon <hi>Dun more</hi> in the County of <hi>Warwick</hi> where Sir <hi>Everard Digby</hi> and his complices had appointed a match of Hunting, that under pretence of that ſport they might come together without any ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, though his minde was Nimrod-like more bent upon the blood of reaſonable men then brute beaſts. For when the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible blow had been given at the Parliament
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121323:20"/>houſe, whereby the King and all the iſſue Male of the Seed Royal had been deſtroyed, their purpoſe was to ſurprize the perſon of the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Kings eldeſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who kept her reſidence at <hi>Combe</hi> the Lord <hi>Harringtons</hi> houſe by <hi>Coventry,</hi> to proclaim her Queen, to provide an Husband for her, ſome Prince of the Popiſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; the Caſtilian was moſt likely to have the refuſal, for to him at this time they were much devoted, and ſo <hi>England</hi> might have been made a province to <hi>Spain.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſtanding all their care, to take a ſolemn Oath, &amp; receive the bleſſed Sacrament for the obſervation of ſecreſie; yet asthe day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the execution of their barbarous cruelty did draw nigh, ſo did the knowlede thereofencreaſe, among the common fort of their own faction, who did meaſure their joy by their hopes of good ſucceſs. For upon this Tueſday morning early, the Papiſts of <hi>Rowington</hi> came to <hi>Warwick</hi> to Ring the Bells, and when Maſter <hi>Themas Hall</hi> the reverend Paſtor of the Church heard who they were that were ringing, he gave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that the Bells ſhould ceaſe, ſaying, that their meaning was Popiſh and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious; but within two daies, he ſound it to be proditorious and mercileſs. Let not any man ſing a triumph before the victory,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121323:20"/>leaſt he be brought to his P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linody or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation. Alſo this morning and much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time, <hi>John Grant</hi> of <hi>Norbrook, Lodowicke Grant</hi> his Brother, and <hi>Henry Morgan</hi> with their aſſociates and ſervants, rode thorough the Town of <hi>Warwick</hi> to <hi>Dunchurch</hi> to joyn with Sir <hi>Everad Digby</hi> and his Complices and thoſe Powder-Men that came down from <hi>London,</hi> who brought them full aſſurance that their main Plot was failed and bewrayed, whereupon they had builded the golden mountains of their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious hopes. Then, and there did they all hold a conſultation what way was beſt for them to take, whether they ſhould ſcatter, and every man ſhift for himſelf, or cluſter together, and ſtand upon their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. They did conclude for the laſt, and ſo turned the ſecret Treaſon into open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
               <p>And for their firſt exploit, by the Advice and Counſell of the <hi>Grants</hi> and <hi>Morgan,</hi> they did reſolve to ſtrengthen themſelves with certain great horſes, that were in the Caſtle ſtable at <hi>Warwick,</hi> which did belong to divers Nobleman and Gentlemen of the Country, who had put them into the hands of one <hi>Henry Bennock</hi> a skilful Rider, to make them fit for their ſervice. <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Compton</hi> had a brace, <hi>Grant</hi> had one
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121323:21"/>there himſelf, and <hi>Morgan</hi> had another, and ſome other Gentlemen had the like, to the number of twelve, or there about.</p>
               <p>And this act of violence and Robbery, <hi>Gram</hi> made no doubt to performe eaſily and ſpeedily (as he did) by the acquaintance he had with <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icholas Smith,</hi> ſervant to <hi>Bennuck,</hi> who lay in the Stable over the horſes. For the Stable at this time did lye opon to the Street, and was not walled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout as now it is. That work of defence, and much more about the Caſtle, both for uſe and ornament, hath been erected ſince by Sir <hi>Fulke Grevill,</hi> Lord <hi>Brooke,</hi> after that by the favor and bounty of King <hi>James</hi> he came to be the owner and poſſeſſor of it. Upon the Tueſday night, or rather the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday morning ſome houres before day. they all came from <hi>Dunchurch</hi> to <hi>Warwick,</hi> and <hi>Grant</hi> and ſome others with him, rode up to the Stable dore, and called to <hi>Smith</hi> the Groom, and ſaid, <hi>Nick,</hi> what, art a bed? a good husband would be up, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Horſes to ride; the Groom know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Grants</hi> voyce, by his often comming to ſee the riding of his owne Horſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting nothing but faire dealing (having alwaies a Candle burning by him in the night in caſe the horſes prove unruly or break looſe) roſe up, and being but half
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121323:21"/>dreſſed opened the Stable dore. Then the Rebels ruſhed in, ſadled all the horſes, and rode away with them to <hi>Norbrook, Grants</hi> houſe, two miles from <hi>Warwick, Weſtward.</hi> Where <hi>Rookwoods</hi> Wife, <hi>Morgans</hi> Wife, and ſome others of the ſame ſtamp were come together, to ſing and rejoyce for the downfall and deſtruction of the Hereticks. But when they ſaw their Husbands much dejected in ſpirit, their countenances fallen, and underſtood the cauſe thereof, their mirth was turned into mourning, and their ſinging into ſighing. Yet did they not ſpare to upbraide them with dulneſs and coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs ſaying; Are you the men that would Conquer Kingdoms, and do you ſtay here? go out for ſhame, encreaſe your forces, and try the uttermoſt of your fortunes.</p>
               <p>This night Maſter <hi>John Norton</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſheriff, (who at this time dwelt at <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi>) lay at the <hi>Swan</hi> in <hi>Warwick,</hi> and being quickly informed of the ryot and robbery committed at the Caſtle Stable, (for all the Town was up in a tumult, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the woful complaint of <hi>Smith</hi> for the loſs of the horſes, and partly by the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and pranſing of the horſes, when they came among the mares) he ſent a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to Sir <hi>Richard Verney</hi> Sheriff of the County, who came to <hi>Norbrooke,</hi> and ſeized
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121323:22"/>upon all the Cattel on the ground, and goods in the houſe; but the Rebels were gone before he came thither, and their Wives became Priſoners to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheriff, from whom I had the information of theſe things.</p>
               <p>He alſo ſent <hi>Reynold Parker</hi> his own Man to Sir <hi>Eulke Grevile</hi> (the Father of <hi>Fulk</hi> Lord <hi>Brooke</hi>) one of the Deputy Lieutenants of the County, who lived at Beauchamps Court a quarter of a mile from <hi>Alcester,</hi> a Market Town Ten miles from <hi>Warwick,</hi> bordering upon the County of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Meſſenger being afraid to go by <hi>Grants</hi> houſe, went over <hi>Barford</hi> bridge to <hi>Stratford,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Alceſter,</hi> where he ſet up his horſe in his Maſters Stable, and ſpake not a word to any of the Town, of what was done at <hi>Warwick,</hi> but went haſtily to <hi>Beauchamps</hi> Court to deliver his meſſage. The old Knight and noble Patriot no ſooner heard of the manner of their taking away of the great horſes, the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and the <hi>Grants</hi> named, whom he knew very well, and alſo called to minde the late boldneſs and inſolencie of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts before him, in his courſe of juſtice, menacing the Adverſaries of the contrary Religion, with the day of revenge for all their ſufferings, by the penal Laws and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121323:22"/>Statutes: but he did preſently conclude from theſe premiſes that they were entred into a practice of Rebellion, and therefore without any delay he ſent <hi>Edward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thington</hi> the Steward of his houſe, to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> to buy ſome Powder, his ſtore at this time being not anſwerable to his deſire, to make his defence againſt ſuch enemies, as he ſuppoſed were now coming towards him. The Meſſenger that came to him from <hi>Warwick,</hi> returned back with his Steward; and when they came into the midſt of the Town, they there ſaw <hi>John Winter</hi> the youngeſt of the three brothers, who was come thither to call a Trumpeter, which he had there placed about a month before to learne to ſound the points of War. They cryed, ſtop the Thief ſtop the Thief, <hi>Winter</hi> floriſhing his naked ſword over his head, rode back with ſpeed to meet his company. The Towneſ men aſſayed to apprehend him, <hi>Henry Eaton</hi> a Blackſmith ſmote at him, but <hi>Edward Walden</hi> one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, ſaluted him with his black ſtaff, the Enſign of his Office, and made his horſe reel out of his way. At this very inſtant came the Head of the Rebels, along the high way that did croſs that end of the Town, and looked aſide; they ſaw <hi>Winter</hi> like to be taken; Then they cryed; Arme,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121323:23"/>arme, arme, and ſo turned into the Town and reſcued him.</p>
               <p>The Townſmen all amazed at their ſudain ſurprizal by ſo gallant a Troop, ſo bravely mounted, knew not what to do, but to ſave themſelves by ſlipping into their houſes. This hurly burly being near the houſe of Maſter <hi>Fulke Madley.</hi> Bayliff of the Town, he came forth and charged them in the Kings name to keep the peace; whereupon one of them ſmote him with the lock end of a Petronel or Horſemans peece, which blow he felt to his dying day. Some of them in their deſperate fury and madneſs would have ſet the Town on fire, but others gave Counſel to depart, ſaying that if Sir <hi>Fulke Grevill</hi> ſhould heare of them, and come ſorth with his men (whom they knew to be alwaies well attended with a brave compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſtout fellowes) the Town and Country would ſide with him, and ſo they might have the worſt.</p>
               <p>Upon their departure the Townſmen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of their ryot and misbehavior at Warwick did ſet a ſtrong watch upon the high-wayes, and preſently took one <hi>Yorke,</hi> and <hi>Ward,</hi> and <hi>Johnſon,</hi> and <hi>Tom Suo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſervant to <hi>Robert Winter</hi> the eldeſt of the three brothers, and ſome of them that came in the Reare, ſeeing their fellows ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121323:23"/>made a retreat, and fled over <hi>Bidford</hi> bridge towards <hi>Campden</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſham;</hi> But the maine Troop (ſuppoſed to be about foureſcore) went eight miles further, to <hi>Huddington</hi> the houſe of <hi>Robert Winter,</hi> within foure miles of <hi>Worcester.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here a neighbor of <hi>Crowle</hi> the next Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſeeing ſuch an unuſual company, of ſtrangers, and perceiving their muttering and whiſpering together, and alſo noting the great waſte they made in the Barne, by putting their horſes to a heap of wheate in the chaff, did reſolve with himſelf (though the way were foul, and the night darke) to go to <hi>Worceſter</hi> to acquaint the Bayliff of the Towne (for then the head-Officer was ſo called) with their number and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>havior, for he did imagine that they had ſome bad buſineſs in hand. Aſſoon as this man came to the Gate of the City, he was apprehended by a watch; for they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Letters of Hue and Cry after the horſes, by a ſpecial meſſenger who went from <hi>Warwick</hi> to <hi>Wich,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Worceſter</hi> about an houre before he came thither. The Watchmen threatned to carry him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrate for a ſpy; he ſhewed ſome unwillingneſs, which made them to drag him with more eagerneſs to that place whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did deſire to goe. And when they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121323:24"/>came to the Convocation houſe, where the Bayliff and his Brethren were in conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, about the ſtrange newes they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Warwick,</hi> he was admitted into their preſence, to whom he made report of what he had heard and ſeen at <hi>Hudding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> which gave them full aſſurance that Rebellion was come into their Country. Wherefore a Meſſenger with all intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence was poſted to Sir <hi>Richard Walſh</hi> Sheriff of the County, who lived on the Weſt ſide of the River Severne, about four miles from <hi>VVorceſter.</hi> And a ſpeedy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration was made, both for their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and alſo for the ſubduement of the approaching enemy.</p>
               <p>Upon the Thurſday morning by the dawning of the day, foure hundred of them kept their Rendezvouz upon <hi>Oddingley</hi> Heath, near to <hi>VVinters</hi> houſe: but before they came thither, the Rebels were fled Northward, thorow the Forreſt of <hi>Fecken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to <hi>Hewell,</hi> the houſe of the Lord <hi>VVin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> and there they took all the Armour they could finde, and carried it away in a Cart, which they brought with them from <hi>Huddington,</hi> &amp; went that night to <hi>Holbeach</hi> the houſe of <hi>Stephen Littleton,</hi> within the edge and confines of <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> about Twenty miles from <hi>VVorceſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:121323:24"/>
               <p> Sir <hi>Richard VValſh</hi> and the <hi>VVigornians</hi> purſued them with as much ſpeed as the ſeaſon of the yeere would give them leave. And when they heard that the Rebells had taken harbour at <hi>Holbeach,</hi> they made their advance to the houſe, and beſieged it, ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring themſelves under the brick-wall which ſurrounded the houſe. And then did they ſummon them by a Trumpeter, to render themſelves to the Sheriff his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Officer; but they returned this ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful anſwer, and ſaid, <q>That he had need of better aſſiſtance, then of thoſe few num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that were with him, before he could be able to command or compell them.</q> The Sheriff and his company being juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, by their arrogant anſwer, did make preparation to give them a furious aſſault; and upon the Friday morning early, many of the Country did come in to their aid. And the other party within the houſe did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe make themſelves ready to give them the repulſe. But as they were drying about two pound weight of Powder a little from the Chimney in their Chamber, by the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the fire, a ſmall coale of fire ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out upon it, which being thereby blown up, ſcorched and burned the faces, the hands, the ſides of <hi>Catesby, Rookwood, Grant,</hi> and divers others of greateſt account a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121323:25"/>them, who were thereby not only made unable for defence, but alſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſcouraged and caſt down. For now they did begin to ſee, the pride of their own heart that had deceived them. Now they did begin to ſee the wrath of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty waxing hot againſt them, who had thus perfumed them with their own ſmoak, and paid them with their own Coyn. And therefore they reſolved no longer to make reſiſtance, but to endeavor to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by flight. <hi>Stephen Littleton</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert VVinter</hi> made an eſcape, and fled to <hi>Hagley</hi> in the County of <hi>VVorceſter,</hi> (where contrary to the Kings Proclamation) they were firſt hid and releived in the Barne of one <hi>Perks:</hi> but doubting of their ſafety thete, (by reaſon of a poore fellow, who had been ſtealing of Conies in the night, and being beaten from his worke by foule wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, came to the Barne, and climbing up into it, to lodge there all night, fell into the hole between two mowes, where they lay hid) they removed themſelves, and were received, harboured, and relieved by <hi>Humphry Littleton</hi> (for diſtinction com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Yellow <hi>Humphrey</hi>) who was the Governor of the houſe in the abſence of Miſtriſs <hi>Littleton</hi> the owner thereof.</p>
               <p>Here they vvere not many daies, but the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121323:25"/>Cook of the houſe did vvonder vvhat uſe this <hi>Humphrey Littleton</hi> ſhould make of ſo many diſhes of meat in his Chamber at every meals time: and to ſatisfie his own curioſity, went ſecretly to his Chamber dore, and peeping thorow they Keyhole, ſaw <hi>Stephen Littleton</hi> and another man with him, at which ſight he was ſo terrified and affrighted, as he knew not what to do. For to reveale them might endanger their lives; and to conceale them might coſt him his own. After ſome debate with his own ſoule, he did reſolve to ſave himſelf harmleſs what ever came of it, and therefore went and diſcloſed them to one <hi>Jobber</hi> of the Town, to whom he had ſome relation, whereupon followed their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and afterward their convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, condemnation, and execution. Let us now return back to <hi>Holbeach,</hi> and ſee how it fared with the reſt of this helliſh ſociety; there ſhall we finde firſt the Elder <hi>Wright</hi> ſlain, ſecondly the younger <hi>Wright</hi> his brother, thirdly <hi>Rookwood,</hi> and laſt of all <hi>Percy</hi> and <hi>Catesby</hi> were ſlain by <hi>John Street</hi> of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> who had charged his Muſquet (as he himſelf told me) with a brace of Bullets, and reſting it upon the Wall by the Gate, ſhot at them as they were coming in rank, and not in file from the dore to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121323:26"/>the Gate; each Bullet (as he thought) killed a man: for which Fact the King gave him two ſhillings a day, during his natural life, to be paid him out of the Exchequer.</p>
               <p>All the reſt of theſe mercileſs Monſters were taken Priſoners by Sir <hi>Richard Walſh</hi> and his company, who did enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ſpoile of the Enemy. Their Horſes, their Armes, their Silver, their Gold becomes a faire booty for the Conquerors, who doe carry them away in triumph to the ordinary Goale of the County: where they ſtaied ſome few daies, and then were ſent to <hi>London,</hi> to be judged by the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the Parliament, whom they would have deſtroyed. Moſt of their Servants, led by their Maſters, had a gracions pardon; But the Arch. Traytors had famous and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable juſtice executed upon them in and about <hi>London,</hi> and ſome of the meaner ſort were ſent back into the ſeveral Counties where they lived to have their tryal and execution there for the ſpreading of the more terror. And <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Agent in promoting this terrible Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, being now a Priſoner in the <hi>Tower,</hi> there made this confeſſion as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="confession">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121323:26"/>
               <head>The Confeſsion of <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> taken the <hi>XXIII.</hi> of <hi>November, 1605.</hi> in the preſence of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors whoſe names are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My moſt honorable Lords,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NOt out of hope to obtain pardon; for ſpeaking of my temporal part, I may ſay, The fault is greater then can be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given; nor affecting hereby the Title of a good Subject; for I muſt redeem my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from as great a danger as I have haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arded the bringing of her into, before I can purchaſe any ſuch opinion: Only at your Honors comand I will briefly ſet down mine own accuſation, and how far I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in this buſineſs; which I ſhall the faithfuller doe, ſince I ſee ſuch courſes are not pleaſing to Almighty God, and that all, or the moſt material parts have been already confeſſed. I remained with my brother in the Country from <hi>Alhallontide</hi> untill the beginning of <hi>Lent,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord 1603. the firſt year of the Kings Raign, about which time Maſter <hi>Caresby</hi> ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, intreating me to come to <hi>London,</hi> where he and other my friends world be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121323:27"/>glad to ſee me. I deſired him to excuſe me, for I found my ſelf not very well diſpoſed; and (which had happned never to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) returned the Meſſenger without my company. Shortly I received another Letter in any wiſe to come. At the ſecond ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons I preſently came up, and found him with Maſter <hi>John Wright</hi> at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> where he brake with me, how neceſſary it was not to forſake our Country (for he knew I had then a reſolution to goe over) but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver her from the ſervitude in which ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, or at leaſt to aſſiſt her with our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt endeavors. I anſwered, that I had often hazarded my life upon far lighter termes; and now would not refuſe any good occaſion, wherein I might doe ſervice to the Catholick cauſe; but for my ſelf I knew no means probable to ſucceed. He ſaid that had bethought him of a way at one Inſtant to deliver us from all our Bonds, and without any forrain helpe to replant again the Catholick Religion; and withall told me in a word, It was to Blow up the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe with Gunpowder; for, ſaid he, in that place have they done us all the miſchief, and perchance God hath deſigned that place for their puniſhment. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at the ſtrangeneſs of the conceit, and told him that true it was, this ſtrake at the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121323:27"/>roote, and would breed a confuſion fit to beget new alterations; But if it ſhould not take effect (as moſt of this nature miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried) the ſcandal would be ſo great which Catholick Religion might hereby ſuſtain, as not only our enemies, but our friends alſo would with good reaſon condemn us. He told me, the nature of the diſeaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſo ſharp a remedy; and asked me if I would give my conſent; I told him yes, in this or what elſe ſoever, if he reſolved upon it, I would veuture my life. But I propoſed many difficulties; as want of an houſe, and of one to cary the Myne, noiſe in the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſuch like. His anſwer was; Let us give an attempt; and where it faileth, paſs no further. But firſt, quoth he, Becauſe we will leave no peaceable and quiet way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tried, you ſhall goe over, and informe the Conſtable of the State of the Catholicks here in <hi>England,</hi> intreating him to ſollicite his Majeſty at his comming hither, that the Penall Lawes may be recalled, and we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the ranck of his other Subjects; withall you may bring over ſome confident Gentleman, ſuch as you ſhall underſtand beſt able for this buſineſs, and named unto me, <hi>M. Fawkes.</hi> Shortly after, I paſſed the Sea, and found the Conſtable at <hi>Bergen</hi> near <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where by helpe of Maſter <hi>Owen</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121323:28"/>I delivered my meſſage, whoſe anſwer was that he had a ſtrict command from his Maſter, to do all good offices for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and for his own part, he thought himſelf bound in conſcience ſo to do, and that no good occaſion ſhould be omitted; but ſpake to him nothing of this matter.</p>
               <p>Returning to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> with Mr. <hi>Owen,</hi> we had ſpeech whether he thought the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable would faithfully helpe us or no. He ſaid he beleeved nothing leſs, and that they ſought only their own ends, holding ſmall account of Catholicks I told him that there were many Gentlemen in <hi>England,</hi> who would not forſake their Country, untill they hadtryed the uttermoſt, &amp; would rather venture their lives, then forſake her in this miſery; And to add one more to our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as a fit man both for Counſel and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of whatſoever we ſhould, do wiſhed for M. <hi>Fawkes,</hi> whom I had heard good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of; he told me the Gentleman deſerved no leſs, but was at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and that if he came not, as happily he might, before my departure, he would ſend him ſhortly after into <hi>England.</hi> I vvent ſoon after to <hi>Oſtend,</hi> vvhere Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> as then vvas not, but came tvvo daies after. I remained vvith him three or foure daies, in vvhich time I asked him if the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121323:28"/>in <hi>England</hi> ſhould do any thing to help themſelves, vvhether he thought the Archduke vvould ſecond them. He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered, no, for all thoſe parts vvere ſo deſirous of peace vvith <hi>England,</hi> as they would endure no ſpeech of other enterpriſe, neither vvere it fit, ſaid he, to ſet any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject afoot novv the peace is upon conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. I told him there vvas no ſuch reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo fell to diſcourſe of other matters, untill I came to ſpeak of Mr. <hi>Fawkes,</hi> vvhoſe company I vviſhed over into <hi>England,</hi> I asked of his ſufficiency in the vvarrs and told him vve ſhould need ſuch as he if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion required, he gave very good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of him. And as vve vvere thus diſcourſing, and I ready to depart for <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> and taking my leave of Sir <hi>William,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fawkes</hi> came into our company, nevv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returned, and ſaluted us. This is the Gentleman ſaid Sir <hi>William,</hi> that you wiſhed for, and ſo we embraced again. I told him ſome good friends of his wiſhed for his company in <hi>England,</hi> and that if he pleaſed to come to <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> we would have further conference, whether I was then going ſo taking my leave of them both; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: and about two daies after came Mr. <hi>Fawkes</hi> to <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> where I told him that we were upon a reſolution to doe ſomewhat
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121323:29"/>in <hi>England,</hi> if the Peace with <hi>Spaine</hi> hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped us not, but had as yet reſolved upon nothing; ſuch or the like talke we paſſed at <hi>Graveling,</hi> where I lay for a winde, and when it ſerved came both in one paſſage to <hi>Greenwich,</hi> near which place we took a pair of Oares, and ſo came up to <hi>London,</hi> and came to Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> whom we found in his lodging; he welcomed us into <hi>England,</hi> and asked me what news from the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I told him, good words, but I feared the deeds would not anſwer. This was the beginning of <hi>Eaſter</hi> Terme, and about the midſt of the ſame Terme (whether ſent for by Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> or upon ſome buſineſs of his own) up came Mr. <hi>Thomas Percy.</hi> The firſt words he ſpake (after he came into our company) was, Shall we alwaies (Gentlemen) talke, and never doe any thing? Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> took him aſide, and had ſpeech about ſomewhat to be done, ſo as firſt we might all take an Oath of ſecreſie, which we reſolved within two or three daies to doe, ſo as there we met behinde Saint <hi>Clements,</hi> Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> Maſter <hi>Percy,</hi> Maſter <hi>Wright.</hi> Maſter <hi>Guy Fawkes,</hi> and my ſelf; and having upon a Primer given each other the Oath of ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in a Chamber where no other body was, we went after into the next room and heard
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121323:29"/>Maſs, and received the bleſſed Sacrament upon the ſame. Then did Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> diſcloſe to Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> and I together with <hi>Jack Wright,</hi> tell to Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> the buſineſs for which we took this Oath, which they both approved. And then w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> ſent to take the houſe which Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> in mine abſence had learned did belong to one <hi>Ferris,</hi> which with ſome difficulty in the end he obtained, and became as <hi>Ferris</hi> before was, Tenant to <hi>Whinniard.</hi> Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> underwent the name of Maſter <hi>Percies</hi> man, calling himſelf <hi>Johnſon,</hi> becauſe his face was the moſt unknown, and received the Keys of the houſe, untill we heard that the Parliament was adjourned to the ſeventh of <hi>February:</hi> At which time we all departed ſeveral waies into the Country, to meet again at the beginning of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme, Before this time alſo it was thought convenient to have a houſe that might anſwer to Maſter <hi>Percies,</hi> where we might make proviſion of Powder and Wood for the Mine, which being there made ready, ſhould in a night be conveyed by boate to the houſe by the Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we were loth to foule that with often going in and out. There was none that we could deviſe ſo fit as <hi>Lambeth,</hi> where Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> often lay, and to be keeper
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121323:30"/>thereof (by Maſter <hi>Catesbies</hi> choice) we received into the number, <hi>Keyes,</hi> as a truſty honeſt man: this was about a month before <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some fortnight after towards the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningof the Terme, Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> and I came to Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> at <hi>Marecrofts,</hi> where we agreed that now was time to begin, and ſit things in order for the Mine: ſo as Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> went to <hi>London,</hi> and the next day ſent for me to come over to him: when I came, the cauſe was, for that the Scottiſh Lords were appointed to ſit in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Union in Maſter <hi>Percies</hi> houſe. This hindred our beginning untill a fortnight before <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> by which time both Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> and Maſter <hi>Wright</hi> were come to <hi>London,</hi> and we againſt their coming had provided a good part of the Powder: ſo as we all five entred with tooles fit to begin our work, having provided our ſelves of Baked meats, the leſs to need ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad. We entred late in the night; and were never ſeen, ſave only Maſter <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> man, untill <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Eve: In which time we wrought under a little entry to the Wall of the Parliament houſe, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped it, as we went with Wood. Whilſt we were together, we began to faſhion our buſineſs, and diſcourſed what we ſhould do
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121323:30"/>after this deed was done. The firſt queſtion was how we might ſurprize the next heire, the Prince haply would be at the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the King his Father, how ſhould we then be able to ſeiſe on the Duke? This burthen Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> undertook, that by his acquaintance, he with another Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would enter the Chamber without ſuſpition, and having ſome dozen others at ſeveral dores to expect his coming, and two or three on horſeback at the Court gate to receive him, he would undertake (the blow being given, until which he would attend in the Dukes Chamber) to carry him ſafe away: for he ſuppoſed moſt of the Court would be abſent, and ſuch as were there not ſuſpecting or unprovided for any ſuch matter.</p>
               <p>For the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it were eaſie to ſurprize her in the Country, by drawing friends together at an Hunting near the Lord <hi>Haringtons;</hi> and <hi>Aſhby,</hi> Maſter <hi>Cates<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi> houſe, being not far off was a fit place for preparation.</p>
               <p>The next was for money and horſes, which if we could provide in any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meaſure (having the Heire apparent) and the firſt knowledge by foure or five daies, was oddes ſufficient.</p>
               <p>Then what Lords we ſhould ſave from
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121323:31"/>the Parliament, which was firſt agreed in general, as many as we could, that were Catholicks, or ſo diſpoſed; But after we deſcended to ſpeake of particulars.</p>
               <p>Next what forrain Princes we ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint with this before, or joyne with after. For this point we agreed, that firſt we could not enjoyn Princes to that ſecreſie, nor oblige them by Oath, ſo to be ſecure of their promiſe; beſides we knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will approve the project or diſlike it. And if they doe allow thereof, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare before might beget ſuſpition; and not to provide till the buſineſs were acted, the ſame letter that carried news of the thing done, might as well intreat their helpe and furtherance <hi>Spain</hi> is too ſlow in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations to hope any good from, in the firſt extremities, and <hi>France</hi> too near and too dangerous, who with the ſhipping of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> we feared of all the world might make away with us. But while we were in the middle of theſe diſcourſes, we heard that the Parliament ſhould be a new adjour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned untill after <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> upon which tidings we broke off both diſcourſe, and working untill after <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi> About <hi>Candlemas</hi> we brought over in a Boat the Powder, which we had provided at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and laid it in Maſter <hi>Percies</hi> houſe, becauſe we were willing to have all our danger in one place.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:121323:31"/>
               <p> We wrought alſo another fortnight in the Mine againſt the ſtone wall, which was very hard to beat thorow; at vvhich time vve called in <hi>Kit Wright,</hi> and near to <hi>Eaſter</hi> as vve vvrought the third time, opportunity vvas given to hire the Cellar, in vvhich vve reſolved to lay the Povvder, and leave the Mine.</p>
               <p>Novv by reaſon that the charge of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining us ſo long together, beſides the number of ſeveral houſes, vvhich for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral uſes had been hired, and buying of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp;c. had laine heavie on Maſter <hi>Cates<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> alone to ſupport; it was neceſſary for him to call in ſome others to eaſe his charge, and to that end deſired leave, that he with Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> and a third, whom they ſhould call, might acquaint whom they thought fit and willing to the buſineſs; for many, ſaid he, may be content that I ſhould know, who would not therefore that all the Company ſhould be acquainted with their names; to this we all agreed. After this Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> laid into the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar (which he had newly taken) a thouſand of Billets, and five hundred of Fagots, and with that covered the Powder, becauſe we might have the houſe free, to ſuffer any one to enter that would. Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:121323:32"/>wiſhed us to conſider, whether it were not now neceſſary to ſend Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> over, both to abſent himſelf for a time, as alſo to acquaint Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> and Maſter <hi>Owen</hi> with this matter. We all agreed that he ſhould (provided that he gave it them with the ſame Oath that we had taken it before) <hi>viz.</hi> to keep it ſecret from all the world. The reaſon why we deſired Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> ſhould be acquaimed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, was, to have him with us ſo ſoon as he could, And for Maſter <hi>Owen,</hi> he might hold good correſpondency after with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Princes. So Maſter. <hi>Fawkes</hi> departed about <hi>Eaſter</hi> for <hi>Flanders,</hi> and returned the latter end of <hi>Anguſt.</hi> He told me that when he arived at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> Sir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> was not returned from <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſo as he uttered the matter only to <hi>Owen,</hi> who ſeemed well pleaſed with the buſineſs, but told him that ſurely Sir <hi>William</hi> would not be acquainted with any Plot, as having buſineſs now afoot in the Court of <hi>England,</hi> but he himſelf would be alwaies ready to tell it him, and ſend him away ſo ſoon as it were done,</p>
               <p>About this time did Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> and Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> meet at the <hi>Bathe,</hi> where they agreed that the company being yet but few, Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> ſhould have the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121323:32"/>thers authority to call in whom he thought beſt. By which Authority he called in after Sir <hi>Everad Digby,</hi> though at what time I know not, and laſt of all Maſter <hi>Francis Threſham.</hi> The firſt promiſed as I heard Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> ſay, fifteen hundred pounds. The ſecond two thouſand pounds; Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> himſelf promiſed all that he could get of the Earle of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> rents, which was about foure thouſand pounds, and to provide many galloping horſes to the number of ten.</p>
               <p>Mean while Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> and my ſelf alone bought ſome new Powder, as ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt to be dampe, and conveyed it into the Cellar, and ſet it in order, as we reſolved it ſhould ſtand. Then was the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament a new prorogued untill the ſift of <hi>November,</hi> ſo as we all went down untill ſome ten daies before when Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> came up with Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> to an houſe by <hi>Enfield</hi>-Chace called <hi>White-webbes,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I came to them; and Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> willed me to enquire whether the young Prince came to the Parliament. I told him that I heard that his Grace thought not to be there. Then muſt we haveour horſes, ſaid Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> beyond the water, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of more company to ſurprize the Prince, and leave the Duke alone.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:121323:33"/>
               <p> Two daies after being Sunday at night, in came one to my Chamber, and told me that a letter had been given to my Lord <hi>Mounteagle</hi> to this effect, That he wiſhed his Lordſhips abſence from the Parliament, becauſe a blow would there be given; which Letter he preſently carried to my Lord of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> On the morrow I went to <hi>VVhite-VVebbes,</hi> and told it Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> aſſuring him withall that the matter was diſcloſed, and wiſhed him in any caſe to forſake his Country. He told me he would ſee further as yet, and reſolved to ſend Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> to try the uttermoſt, proteſting if the part belonged to himſelf, he would try the ſame adventure.</p>
               <p>On Wedneſday Maſter <hi>Fawkes</hi> went and returned at night of which we were very glad. Thurſday I came to <hi>London,</hi> and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> Maſter <hi>Threſham</hi> and I met at <hi>Barnet,</hi> where we queſtioned how this letter ſhould be ſent to my Lord <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teagle,</hi> but could not conceive; for Maſter <hi>Threſham</hi> forſware it, whom we only ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p>On Saturday night I met Maſter <hi>Threſham</hi> againe in <hi>Lincolns</hi>-Inne walkes. Wherein he told me ſuch ſpeeches that my Lord of <hi>Salisbury</hi> ſhould uſe to the King, as I gave it loſt the ſecond time, and repeated the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121323:33"/>ſame to Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> who hereupon was reſolved to be gone, but ſtaid to have Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> come up, whoſe conſent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we wanted. On Sunday Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> being dealt with to that end, would needs abide the uttermoſt tryal.</p>
               <p>This ſuſpition of all hands put us into ſuch confuſion, as Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> reſolved to goe down into the Country the Monday that Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> went to <hi>Syon,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Percy</hi> reſolved to follow the ſame night or early the next morning. About five of the Clock being Tueſday came the younger <hi>Wright</hi> to my Chamber, and told me that a Nobleman, called the Lord <hi>Mounteagle,</hi> ſaying, Ariſe, and come along to <hi>Eſſex</hi>-houſe, for I am going to call up my Lord of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> ſaying withall, The matter is diſcovered. Goe back Maſter <hi>Wright</hi> (quoth I) and learne what you can about <hi>Eſſex</hi> gate. Shortly he returned and ſaid; Surely all is loſt; for <hi>Lepton</hi> is got on horſeback at <hi>Eſſex</hi> door, and as he parted he asked if their Lordſhips would have any more with him: and being anſwered no, is rode faſt up <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> as he can ride. Goe you then (quoth I) to Maſter <hi>Percy,</hi> for ſure it is for him they ſeek, and bid him be gone, I will ſtay and ſee the uttermoſt.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121323:34"/>Then I went to the Court gates and found them ſtraightly garded, ſo as no body could enter. From thence I went down towards the Parliament-houſe, and in the middle of <hi>Kingsſtreet,</hi> found the Guard ſtanding that would not let me paſs. And as I retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned I heard one ſay, there is a Treaſon diſcovered, in which the King and the Lords ſhould have been blows up. So then I was fully ſatisfied that all was known, and went to the Stable where my Gelding ſtood, and rode into the Country, Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> had appointed our meeting at <hi>Dunchurch,</hi> but I could not overtake them untill I came to my Brothers, which was Wednesday night. On Thursday we took the Armor at my Lord <hi>Winſors,</hi> and went that night to one <hi>Stephen Littletous</hi> houſe, where the next day (being Friday) as I was early abroad to diſcover, my man came to me and ſaid, that a heavy miſchance had ſevered all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for that Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> Maſter <hi>Rook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Grant</hi> were burned with Gunpowder, upon which ſight the reſt diſperſed. Maſter <hi>Littleton</hi> wiſhed me to flie, and ſo would he. I told him, I would firſt ſee the body of my Friend and bury him, whatſoever befell me.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121323:34"/>When I came, I found Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable well, Maſter <hi>Percy,</hi> both the <hi>Wrights,</hi> Maſter <hi>Rookwood,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Grant.</hi> I asked them what they reſolved to doe; they anſwered, we meane here to dye; I ſaid again, I would take ſuch part as they did.</p>
               <p>About eleven of the clock came the company to beſet the houſe, and as I walked into the Court, I was ſhot into the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which loſt me the uſe of mine Arme: the next ſhot was the elder <hi>Wright</hi> ſtricken dead, after him the younger Maſter <hi>Wright,</hi> and fourthly <hi>Ambroſe Rookwood.</hi> Then ſaid Maſter <hi>Catesby</hi> to me (ſtanding before the dore they were to enter) ſtand by me <hi>Tom,</hi> and we will die together. Sir (quoth I) I have loſt the uſe of my right Arme, and I feare that will cauſe me to be taken. So as we ſtood cloſe together. Maſter <hi>Catesby,</hi> Maſter <hi>Percy,</hi> and my ſelf, they two were ſhot (as far as I could gueſs, with one Bullet) and then the company entred upon me, hurt me in the Belly with a Pike, and gave me other wounds untill one came behind, and caught hold of both mine armes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo Iremaine yours, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:121323:35"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Commiſſ.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Somerſet</hi> Earle of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Notingham,</hi> Lord Admiral.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> Lord Privie Seale.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Secretary.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Erskeine</hi> Earle of <hi>Marre</hi> and <hi>Garioth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Conſtable</hi> Viſcount <hi>Dunbar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Popham</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice.</item>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121323:35"/>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> Atturney General.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Waad,</hi> Lievtenant of the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The names of thoſe that were firſt in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and laboured in the Myne.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Catesby</hi> Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Winter</hi> Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> Gentlemen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> Gentlemen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Wright</hi> Gentlemen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chriſtopher Wright</hi> Gentlemen</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Guido Fawkes</hi> And <hi>Bates Catesbies</hi> man.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:121323:36"/>
               <p> The names of thoſe that were made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, though not perſonally labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the Myne nor in the Cellar.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Everard Digby</hi> Knight.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ambroſe Rookwood</hi> Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Treſham</hi> Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stephen Littleton</hi> Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Grant</hi> Gent.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Keyes</hi> Gent.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Sir <hi>Everad Digby</hi> and ſome others of the chiefeſt were executed in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard,</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121323:36"/>
               <p> The Names of thoſe that did riſe in Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, and alſo of thoſe that did har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and releeve ſome of them contrary to the Kings Proclamations poſted down into the Country.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lodow. Grant,</hi> Gent. Executed at <hi>Warwi.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>H. Morgan.</hi> Gent. Executed at <hi>Warwi.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Winter,</hi> Gent. Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Worceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hum. Littleton,</hi> Gent. Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Worceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perks</hi> of <hi>Hagley,</hi> and <hi>Burford</hi> his man. Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Worceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Smart</hi> and <hi>lihead.</hi> Executed at <hi>Stafford,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121323:37"/>
               <p> For harboring and releeving <hi>Robert Winter,</hi> and <hi>Stephen Littleton</hi> at <hi>Weſt-Bramwich</hi> before they fled to <hi>Hagley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When theſe monſtrous offenders were made examples of famous and honorable juſtice; the King and the Parliament took ſpecial care to find out ſuch Popiſh Divines as gave Counſel and countenance to this unheard of villany. For it is proper to all the Treaſons attempted in <hi>England,</hi> to have ſome Romiſh Prieſt or Jeſuite in the practice. The Devill who was a Murtherer from the beginning, will evermore make choice of the fitteſt inſtruments that may be, for the bringing of his curſed and cruel deſignes into action. Not the dull Aſſe, not the heavy Oxe, not the ſilly ſheep, but the ſubtile ſerpent muſt help to ſet forward his work of temptation.</p>
               <p>Many of theſe Incendiaries inſpired by the powers of darkneſs with a tranſcendent rage againſt the State, being chaſed with the guiltineſs of their own conſciencies, fled from their triall into forraine Countries for their better ſafety. Father <hi>Creſwell</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf into the habit of a Merchant took ſhipping at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and wafted into <hi>Spaine,</hi> where he had been leiger Jeſuite a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121323:37"/>little before, and came into <hi>England</hi> at this time to beare his part with the reſt of his ſociety in a victoral ſong, or ſong of thanksgiving, for the extirpation and rooting out of thoſe, who do worſhip God after that way which they call Hereſie.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Garnet</hi> and <hi>Oldcerne</hi> two of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal were apprehended at <hi>Henlip</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> in Mr <hi>Abingtons</hi> houſe, where they were immured and cloſed up in a ſtack of Chymnies, the way or paſſage into the Cave or Vault where they lay, was in an upper room or chamber, by taking up the half pace before the hearth, whoſe wooden border was made like to a trap-door, to pluck up, and let down, and then the bricks were laid in their courſes and order again. Such holes have theſe Foxes made for their hiding places.</p>
               <p>Upon their examination and confeſsion of their own guiltineſs of their foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and concealment of this ſo deteſtable a Treaſon, they did both ſuffer condigne puniſhment; and <hi>Garnet</hi> (whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was great and Reverend with <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesby,</hi> and the reſt of the Arch. Traytors was executed in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard upon the third of <hi>May</hi> next enſuing the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Plot. He was a man (ſaith
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121323:38"/>the Un-Jeſuited Cardinal) incomparable for learning of all kindes; but ſurely had he had leſs learning and more grace, he would never have had a hand in ſo foul a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>As for the gentle hearted Jeſuite <hi>Parſons,</hi> who had dipt his pen in gall againſt our moſt renowned Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kept himſelf without the reach and jerke of the rod of Juſtice, and dyed ſhortly after at <hi>Rome,</hi> in that old Houſe which was converted to a New-Colledge by Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the thirteenth (as we have ſaid before) whereof he was Rector, much grieved, (no doubt) for that their holy Enterprize did ſo miſcarrie. And <hi>Owen</hi> brother to <hi>Owen</hi> of <hi>Godſtow</hi> by <hi>Oxford</hi> ſucceeded him in that place, and to him ſucceeded <hi>Fitz-Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Baldwine</hi> who was of the Councel of this horrible Treaſon whiles he lurked in the Low-Countries, was many years after apprehended at <hi>Baſil</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> as he was going up into <hi>Italy;</hi> and being brought into <hi>England,</hi> and falling into the hands of a mercifull Prince, found more favor then he deſerved. For by the means and mediation of Don <hi>Gondomar</hi> the Spaniſh Ambaſſador, an honorable Spy,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121323:38"/>the King granted him his pardon. And the Ambaſſador with all his train went to the priſon, and with great veneration brought him forth and ſet him at liberty, which made the account of his Ambaſſage, the more acceptable to the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> Preſident of the grand Counſel of <hi>Spain,</hi> when he returned home.</p>
               <p>We have now ſeen how much was wrought to have turned the Parliament-Houſe into a Slaughter-houſe, to have brought our Nation under the calamity of Antichriſtian ſervitude, and once more to have clapt the Popes Saddle upon <hi>Englands</hi> back, which if God Almighty had ſuffered for our ſins to have been brought to paſs; then might our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, have ſaid (and that truly) that the Divel did ride us.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the greatneſs of this Treaſon, ſo great as no hiſtory can equal, yet ſome of the Traytors, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler then the earth,<note place="margin">See King <hi>James</hi> his premoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology. <hi>pag.</hi> 78.</note> at the time of their death, would not ask God or King forgiveneſs, nor acknowledg that they had done any fault unleſs the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould firſt condemn it,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121323:39"/>as if Treaſon were no Treaſon, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der were no Murder, unleſs the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> judg it to be ſo.</p>
               <p>Never was there any Sect or ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the World, neither <hi>Turk,</hi> nor <hi>Jew,</hi> nor <hi>Infidel,</hi> no not thoſe of <hi>Calicute</hi> which worſhip the Devil, that did hold it lawful, or rather meritorious to kill Prince or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for quarrel of Religion, the Papiſts only excepted, who do palliate and cover all their perfidious practiſes, with the fair pretext of conſcience and the good of the Catholick cauſe. When did the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is commonly called the <hi>Pope,</hi> ever call any of theſe Prieſts and Jeſuites in queſtion, that fled hence into <hi>Italy,</hi> who were Fomenters of this damnable Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, much leſs puniſhed them for it? What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is done in favor of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt be accounted well done, though never ſo ill done.</p>
               <p>His Holineſs (ſo called by an antiphraſe) and his Paraſites will command bloody Maſſacres, will commend Treaſon and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; Pope Innocent the third, who lived in the time of our King <hi>John,</hi> and was his great and troubleſome Enemy, decreed an immortal war againſt the poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121323:39"/>that went under the names of <hi>Valden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> or <hi>Albigeans.</hi> charging them with all kindes of Hereſies, becauſe they blamed and deteſted the Vices and Errors of the Pope and his Clergy. Many Princes are commanded by the Pontifical Authority to arme againſt them, and the Croiſado is preached againſt them, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Infidels.<note place="margin">See the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>France. pag.</hi> 125. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 131.</note> This was in the year of our Lord a thouſand two hundred and ten. <hi>Simon</hi> Earl of <hi>Montfort</hi> is choſen Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Army, who enters into <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedoc,</hi> and there beſieges <hi>Bezeirs</hi> with ſuch cruel ſucceſs, as having taken it, the blood flowed by the loſs of threeſcore thouſand perſons. And when preparation was made for a new ſearch, to root out the remainder of them, <hi>Lewis</hi> the ninth of <hi>France</hi> (commonly called St <hi>Lewis</hi>) would not give allowance to any further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt them within his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſaying, that they muſt be perſwaded by reaſon, and not conſtrained by violence. For piety is a duty of man unto God, over which worldly force hath no power.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth mnde a Panegyrick Oration in his conſiſtory, wherein he did praiſe and commend the Diveliſh Fryer,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121323:40"/>an excrement of Hell,<note place="margin">See King <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Apol. pag.</hi> 67 <hi>&amp; pa.</hi> 75.</note> that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered King <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France</hi> by ſheathing a knife in the bottom of his belly.</p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Richard Allen,</hi> an Engliſh Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive, being honored by the Pope with the degree of a red hat, was not aſhamed to publiſh in print, an Apology for Sir <hi>William Starlies</hi> treaſon, maintaining that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Hereſie, it was not only lawfull for any of her Subjects, but they were even bound in conſcience to deprive her of any ſtrength which lay in their power to do. And whether it were armies, towns, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes of hers, which they had in their hands they were obliged to put them in the King of <hi>Spain</hi> her Enemies hand, ſhe no more being the right owner of any thing. But whatſoever the Cardinal ſaith; the beſt policy is to be an honeſt man.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Oldcorn</hi> that refined and ſublimated Fryer, preached Treaſon upon Treaſon, and Rebellion upon Rebellion. For after the diſcovery of this horrid intended Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, and a little before notice was given to the Sheriff of the County, of his hiding, and for his apprehenſion, at <hi>Henlip</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, he did there preach conſolitary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121323:40"/>to his popiſh Anditory, exhorting them not to faint for the miſgiving of this Enterpriſe nor think the worſe thereof,<note place="margin">See King <hi>James</hi> his Premoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>pag,</hi> 127 <hi>&amp;</hi> 128.</note> that it ſucceeded not alleaging diverſe Preſidents of ſuch godly enterpriſes that miſgave in like manner; eſpecially, that of St <hi>Lewis</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> who in his journey to the holy Land, was taken priſoner by the Sultan of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the greateſt part of his Army was deſtroyed by the Plague, and thereupon exhorted and perſwaded them, not to give over, but ſtill to hope that God would bleſs their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize at ſome other time, though this did fail.</p>
               <p>By theſe demonſtrations we may know the mind of all of that profeſſion, and what they would do, if they had the power in their hands, and were Lords over us. When they want force of argument, and ſound reaſon to perſwade us, they will then uſe force of arms, fire and ſword, treaſon and rebellion to deſtroy us, which ſhould rouſe up our ſpirits, and ingender in our hearts; Firſt a deteſtation of the bloody, but cherlie, and moſt ignoble practiſes of the Pope and his Adherents. Secondly, gratulation and thanksgiving to the moſt high God, who
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121323:41"/>hath hitherto compaſſed us about with ſongs of deliverance. And laſtly, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, caution, valour and vigilance for the time to come that we be not ſuddenly ſurprized, and ſwallowed up quick of our implacable Enemies, while we dally and play with Popery. The Scorpion is not without a ſting, though he doth not always ſtrike. A <hi>Cain,</hi> a <hi>Cataline,</hi> a <hi>Catesby,</hi> full of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity, hating with cruel hatred, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be working ſome great miſchief. And therefore to our own ſafety and ſecurity, our own diligence and ſedulitie is evermore required.</p>
               <p>Their thoughts are vain who think that their watching can preſerve the City, which God himſelf is not willing to keep. And are not theirs as vain, who think that God will keep that City, for which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not carefull to watch? The providence of the Almighty muſt be ſerved with the uſe of lawful means.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:121323:41"/>
            <head>In the Third YEAR of KING <hi>JAMES.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">An ACT for a publicke Thanks-giving to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, on the fifth day of <hi>November</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Year.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as Almighty God hath in all Ages ſhewed his Power and Mercy, in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous and gracious deliverance of his Church, and in the protection of Religious Kings and States. And that no Nation of the earth hath been bleſſed with greater benefits then this Kingdom now enjoyeth, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true and free profeſſion of the Goſpel under our moſt Soveraigne Lord, King <hi>James,</hi> the moſt Great,
<pb facs="tcp:121323:42"/>Learned, and Religious King that ever reigned therein, inriched with a moſt hopeful and plentiful Progenie, proceeding out of his Royal loynes, promiſing continuance of this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and profeſsion to all poſterity: the which many Malignant and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh Papiſts, Ieſuites nnd Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſts much envying and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, conſpired moſt horribly, when the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, the Queen, the Prince, and all the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſhould have been aſſembled in the Vpper-Houſe of Parliament upon the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> in the Year of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred and five, ſuddainly to have blown up the ſaid whole houſe with Gun-powder; an invention ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, barbarous, and cruel, as the like was never before heard of, and was (as ſome of the principal Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors thereof confeſſe) purpoſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and concluded to be done in the
<pb facs="tcp:121323:42"/>ſaid Houſe, that where ſundry, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and Religious Laws for preſervation of the Church and State were made, which they falſely and ſtanderouſly term cruel Laws, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted againſt them and their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, both place and perſons ſhould be all deſtroyed and blown up at once, which would have turned to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rume of this whole Kingdom, had it not pleaſed Almighty God, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty with a Divine ſpirit, to interpret ſome dark phraſes of a Letter ſhewed to his Maieſty, above and beyond all ordinary conſtruction, thereby miraculouſly diſcovering this hidden treaſon not many hours before the appointed time for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thereof: Therefore the Kings moſt excellent Maieſty, the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and all his Maieſties faithfull and loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, do moſt iuſtly acknowledg this great and infinite Bleſſing to have
<pb facs="tcp:121323:43"/>proceeded meerly from God his great mercy, and to his moſt holy name do aſcribe all Honor, Glory and Praiſe: and to the end, this unfeigned thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs may never be forgotten, but be had in a perpetual remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, that all ages to come may yield praiſes to his Divine Maieſty for the ſame, and have in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all memory, This joyful day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame, that all and ſingular Miniſters in every Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral and Pariſh Church, or other uſuall place for common Prayer, within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and the Dominions of the ſame, ſhall always upon the fifth day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> ſay morning Prayer, and give unto Almighty God, thanks
<pb facs="tcp:121323:43"/>for this moſt happy Deliverance.</p>
            <p>And that all and every Perſon and Perſons inhabiting within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the ſame, ſhall always upon that day, diligently and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſort to the Pariſh Church or Chappel accuſtomed, or to ſome uſual Church or Chappel where the ſaid Morning Prayer, preaching or other ſervice of God ſhall be uſed, then and there to abide orderly and ſoberly, during the time of the ſaid Prayers, preaching, or other ſervice of God there to be uſed and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred.</p>
            <p>And becauſe all and every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be put in mind of this Duty, and be the better prepared to the ſaid Holy Service, Be it enacted by authority aforeſaid, that every Miniſter ſhall give warning to his Pariſhoners publikely in the Church at Morning Prayer, the Sunday before every ſuch fifth day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:121323:44"/>for the due obſervation of the ſaid Day. And that after Morning Prayer, or preaching upon the ſaid fifth day of <hi>November,</hi> they read diſtinctly and plainly this preſent ACT.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121323:44"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
